My dear children,
it is now better than several years
since l moved to New York
and l haven't seen you
as much as l would like to.
l hope you will come to this ceremony
of Papal honours,
given for my charitable work.
The only wealth in this world is children.
More than all the money and power
on Earth.
You are my treasure.
Anthony and Mary,
although l entrusted your education to
your mother for your own best interest,
l look forward to seeing you, and to
a new period of harmony in our lives.
Perhaps you might prevail upon your
mother to come to this celebration,
and that from time to time, we can all
see each other at family functions.
Anyway, l remain your loving father.
Hail Mary, full of grace...
...blessed art Thou amongst women...
...and blessed is the fruit of Thy womb,
Jesus.
Holy Mary, mother of God,
pray for us sinners...
Almighty God, bless the insignia
of Saint Sebastian the Martyr,
that it may contribute to the sacredness
of him to whom it is given.
Do you, Michael, promise to be faithful
to the noble purposes of this Order,
to have a special care for the poor,
the needy and those who are ill?
l do so promise.
May the blessing of Almighty God,
Father, Son and Holy Spirit
descend upon you
and remain with you forever.
Vincent, our name is not on the list.
Write it in. Mancini. M-A-N-C-l-N-l.
- Problem?
- My name isn't on the list.
- Then you have to leave immediately.
- You want to dance with me?
Joe, it's Vinnie. These are our guests.
l'm sorry. l'm sorry, sir.
Welcome to the party.
- lt's good to see you.
- Good to see you. This is my husband.
- Sit down.
- My son, Anthony.
The Order of Saint Sebastian is one of
the highest honours the Church awards.
lt was first granted by Pope...
What about Mr Corleone's connections
with gambling?
The press kits have...
- And involvement with the underworld?
- Cut the crap.
The Pope, the Holy Father himself,
has today blessed Michael Corleone.
Do you know better than the Pope?
Vincent! She loves you.
Yeah?
l love you too.
Hi, Vincent. l remember you.
- From where?
- The last party we were at together.
- Did you come to the club?
- No, it was a wedding.
l was eight and you were 1 5.
l had many girlfriends when l was 1 5.
- Eight-year-olds?
- Especially them.
Where's Mary?
Would somebody please hail Mary?
Excuse me, Your Excellency.
You haven't kissed me hello yet.
Relatives always kiss.
- Now we're related?
- l'm your little cousin.
- Who's your father?
- l'll give you a hint.
He's ltalian.
Mary, we've been waiting for you.
Remember to keep your voice low.
And smile. Don't forget to smile.
The honorary chairman of
the Vito Corleone Foundation:
my daughter, Mary Corleone.
Thanks.
l think l inherited my father's love
for speechmaking. Here it goes.
The Vito Corleone Foundation helps
the poor in every country,
gives grants to artists,
funds medical research,
and is particularly dedicated
to the resurrection of Sicily.
Archbishop Gilday,
here is 1 00 million dollars for the poor
of Sicily, in the name of Vito Corleone.
Don't spend it all in one place.
Mary, l'm so proud of you.
Michael...
You've done a wonderful thing for Sicily.
Let's hope that the money gets
to the people who need it.
Amen.
...the most important part:
Johnny Fontane!
Thank you very much.
l'm happy to be here.
l would like you to join me in honouring
Commendatore Michael Corleone.
l have something special
for our godfather.
l happen to know his favourite song.
Michael, where are you going?
l'm off to the kitchen
to hear some Tony Bennett records.
Your favourite song: ''Salsiccia's Own''.
l'm having a salsiccia sandwich.
l'll be back.
Hello, Kay.
Congratulations, Michael.
That's quite an honour.
But a little expensive, wouldn't you say?
- Cake?
- No, thank you.
- lt's been a long time, hasn't it?
- Yeah.
- Eight years.
You look wonderful.
Your son has something he wants to
talk to you about. l came here for him.
- What's wrong with being a lawyer?
- He wants his life to be in music.
Music is great, l love music.
But he should finish what he started.
Anthony...
- l'm going my own way.
- Your own way?
- Professional singer?
- Yes.
What happens if you fail?
- l won't fail.
- Men always believe that.
A law degree is like taking out insurance.
- After that you can work for me...
- l will never work for you.
l have bad memories.
Every family has bad memories.
l'll always be your son, but won't have
anything to do with your business.
Anthony... finish the law degree.
No.
Well, that he got from you. That ''no''.
- You could've helped me convince him.
- Convince him of what?
Of what?
He throws his life away.
He throws greatness away.
This is greatness?
Now that you're so respectable,
you're more dangerous than ever.
l preferred you when you were
just a common Mafia hood.
Okay.
- Can we talk common sense here?
- All right.
Tony knows that you killed Fredo.
- What did you come here for?
- To protect my son.
Not to see you disguised by your
church. That was a shameful ceremony.
l spent my life protecting my son.
l spent my life protecting my family!
Let's be reasonable, okay?
That's your big thing, isn't it, Michael?
Reason.
- Backed up by murder.
- Oh, God.
- You hate me. You hate me.
- No.
l don't hate you.
l dread you.
l did what l could, Kay, to protect all
of you from the horrors of this world.
But you became my horror.
The children still love you, though.
Especially Mary.
That's something.
We can build on that. For their sake.
Let's try.
Only if you let Tony go free to have
his own life, away from you.
l'll let Tony go.
Thank you.
- Hi.
You could hurt somebody with those.
Let me show you around.
Can you get me an interview
with Corleone?
No. l'm a relative, but l can't do that.
What else can l do for you?
- Handsome, but useless.
- Oh, yeah?
- That's okay, l'll gamble.
- Do you like to gamble?
Let's go to Atlantic City.
l'll show you how to gamble.
- How will l know what numbers to bet?
- Do l look like a loser?
Well...
Spooky-looking guy there.
- What's a guy like that doing here?
- That's Joey Zasa's bulldog.
- You know him?
- Yeah, l do.
His name is Anthony Squigilaro.
They call him ''The Ant''.
He dips his bullets in cyanide.
Don Altobello.
- l've come to pay my respects.
- Grazie.
You honour my father's friendship.
Where is my god-daughter?
- Constanza!
- Don Altobello.
lt was not so long ago
that l held you in these old hands.
Michael, l've lost all the venom,
all the juice of youth.
l've lost the lust for women,
and now my mind is clear.
My duty to God is clear.
l have a special favour to ask of you.
Can l attach my name
to the Vito Corleone Foundation,
so that you and l can be joined
in name and spirit?
- One million dollars.
- A lot of money...
- Godfather.
- Don Altobello, you have such a heart.
Come, let's go and sample
some of that old vino.
The Vatican knows nothing
about these shareholders.
Good.
l have a tendency to worry. We've
increased our position substantially.
- Naturally, l worry.
- Stop worrying, we have an agreement.
Good. How do you think
l got this grey hair?
Two seconds... Thank you for your
contribution to the swimming-pool.
We need your help on Sam Wallace's
candidacy for judgeship.
- We can always use a good judge.
- Thanks.
Andrew!
My godson Andrew Hagen.
My brother Tom's eldest boy.
He's been assistant to Bishop Breelan
for three years.
- Hopes to be assigned to the Vatican.
- Rome needs fine young priests.
His mother Theresa Hagen,
Bishop Gilday.
Honoured to meet you.
Mr Corleone. Hi. Grace Hamilton.
Vincent Mancini promised to tell you
about me, that maybe you'd see me.
- Did Vincent Mancini call about her?
- No.
- You promised to stay out there, twice.
- l know.
Joey Zasa showed up.
He's waiting in the lobby.
He wants to personally
congratulate you. Show his respect.
- Do l have to see him?
- He says you're his patron.
Hey, Vinnie!
- Who's your favourite aunt?
- You are.
Today l'll talk to Michael
about your little problem.
lf you'd warned me, l would have
worn a better suit.
The Meucci Association
has elected you
ltalian-American Man of the Year.
Meucci...
Who's Meucci?
The ltalian-American who invented
the telephone, one year before Bell.
And this is the reason
you've come today?
l...
l've got a stone in my shoe.
A two-bit punk who works for me.
The one who thinks he's related to you.
A bastard.
He's here. Vincent Mancini.
He's at the party.
Bring him in.
l think it's good that we talk.
No, grazie.
l have a problem...
...and l want to find out if it is
my problem or your problem.
Your business is your business. l have
no interests or percentages from it.
Good. Then it's my problem.
Michael, you know Vincent Mancini.
Sonny's boy.
- How are you, Mr Corleone?
- How are you?
- Good. How are you? Good party.
- You like it?
- Yes, l had to sneak in.
- You're dressed for it.
So, what's the trouble
between you and Mr Joe Zasa?
- Just trouble. l'll take care of it.
- That's foolish of you.
Foolish of me? lt's a little foolish
of this guy, don't you think? Right?
- Right?!
- Temper like his father...
Vincent...
Mr Joe Zasa now owns what used to
be the Corleone business in New York.
Out of kindness, he gave you
a job in his family.
You took it against my advice.
l offered you something better in the
legitimate world. You turned me down.
Now you both come to me with this bad
blood. What do you expect me to do?
- Am l a gangster?
- No...
That was Papa's neighbourhood.
Zasa runs it like a disgrace!
- That's the past, Connie.
- l earned that territory.
The Commission gave it to me
and you approved.
Yes.
l came for the party, not to ask for help.
l could kill this bastard.
So kill him.
What does all this have to do with me?
Well, he goes behind your back,
saying ''Fuck Michael Corleone''.
Say it to his face, one time!
Mr Corleone, all bastards are liars.
Shakespeare wrote poems about it.
What am l going to do with this guy?!
Joey, if there's some guy
running around this city,
saying ''Fuck Michael Corleone''...
...what do we do
with a piece of shit like that?
He's a fucking dog.
Yes, it's true. lf anyone would say
such a thing,
they would not be a friend,
they would be a dog.
- My interests don't conflict with his.
- You don't know how much they do.
Quiet, Vincent.
He needs your support!
Don't let me work for this guy,
let me work for you.
As what? Tough guy? l don't need
tough guys. l need more lawyers.
Since we have no conflicts or debts,
l accept your tribute. l wish you well.
Vincent, make your peace
with Mr Joe Zasa. Go on.
Bastardo...
Vinnie, what's the matter with you?!
Get him out of here.
Jesus Christ...
- l told Connie this wasn't the right time.
- Close it.
l know you're into Wall Street,
but you're still the final word.
l want to protect you from these guys.
Your lawyers can't.
- But you can?
- Yeah, l can do that.
Why should l be afraid of Zasa?
You stop him from rising
in the Commission.
l say we make him dead.
Give me the order, l'll do it.
- You'll do it?
- Yeah.
Maybe you should come with me
for a few weeks. See what happens.
- Okay.
- See if you learn.
And we'll talk about your future.
l won't let you down.
lt's about ready.
What happened?
lf l'm in a room with Zasa,
what happens? l bit his ear off.
Here we go. Watch the card.
Hold it!
- Vincent...
- Yeah.
Take the picture with us.
Nice jacket.
Closer to the centre, sir.
Smile!
Godfather, this is the cake for you
and your family from Enzo the baker.
Do you want to do it?
Cent'anni! Cent'anni!
- Vincent?
- What do you want, sweetheart?
Do you love me?
- Come on, go to bed.
- Come on, say it.
l love you.
l love you, too.
You've got a cat?
Go get us some water, l'm thirsty.
Come on.
Well, l guess l know my place.
l can't believe l'm actually doing this.
''Get me water, bake me a cake''...
What happened to ''please''?
Good boy, Sackface. Go for a walk.
- Let her go.
- Cut her throat, man.
- What did you say?
- Cut her fucking throat.
- Okay, chief...
- Drop your gun or he'll cut her throat.
l hardly know her, so cut her.
What the fuck do l care?
You've got no choice. She'll be dead.
lf you do, l'll kill you both.
Give up that knife, l'll let you go.
Cut her throat! Right now!
l'll do something that'll convince you.
Don't get frightened. Just watch me.
Oh, shit!
Drop the knife. Drop it!
Good boy. Sit down, l want to talk
to you. lt was a wise choice. Sit down.
Lose the mask.
Relax, have a smoke. You smoke?
Whose idea was this? Who sent you?
Tell me who sent you.
- No one.
- Did you take a look at this guy?
- Yeah.
- Who sent you?
lt was Joey Zasa.
Are you okay?
- You were going to let them kill me!
- No, l wasn't...
You pig! You sick fuck!
You wanted gambling. That's gambling.
Call the police.
- You killed the other guy too?
- He went for my gun.
lt was self-defence.
Go ahead, call the police.
- No, no...
- l'm taking pictures.
No pictures.
You had a gun!
They only had a knife. You could have
handed them over to the police.
Zasa sent them.
l just sent him a message.
- Now he has to send you one back.
- ls Zasa going to send me one back?
He did the right thing.
He got Zasa's name!
What has Joey Zasa to do
with anything? Joey Zasa is a pazzo.
All right. You are what you are.
lt's your nature. Stay close to me.
Don't do anything. Keep your mouth
shut and your eyes open.
- And you do what l tell you.
- l understand.
- l have problems with the Commission.
- l know.
- You don't make them easier.
- lt wasn't my idea that this happened.
- Get out of here.
- Michael...
Yes?
- Now they'll fear you.
- Maybe they should fear you.
- B.J., what's up?
- The Archbishop just called back.
We've arranged some amazing things.
The publicity is phenomenal. You're the
new Rockefeller. A philanthropist.
- Sign here, please.
- Times do change, don't they?
My father hated foundations.
He loved doing it by himself.
Man to man. But we're different.
No different than any large corporation.
We control a lot of money with little.
Minimise taxes.
With no government control.
- Godfather.
- Andrew.
- Off to Rome...
- l wanted to thank you for everything.
- Do you want some breakfast?
- Thanks, l can't.
- How's your ltalian?
- Devo fare un po' di pratica.
- His father was a great lawyer.
- l know.
Didn't live to see him ordained. l did.
Did you ever see one of those?
Beautiful. l was so proud.
Let me walk you out.
lf you hear any rumours in the Vatican,
let me know.
No, Andrew has the true faith.
Don Corleone,
l need your help. And not just
to light a little candle.
My gift was to be able to persuade
people to give to the Holy Church.
Then Rome decides to put me
in charge of the Vatican Bank...
...but l was never a true banker.
Mea culpa. l trusted my friends.
Friendship and money...
Oil and water...
lndeed.
But these ''friends'' used the good name
of the Church to feed their greed.
lf money was lost...
...then l am to blame.
lf only prayer could pay off
our 700 million dollar deficit.
769 million...
The Church owns 25 percent
of a large corporation: lmmobiliare.
You know the one l mean?
Largest landlord on Earth.
Real estate worth six billion dollars.
That's true.
And the Vatican vote
is necessary for control.
No, you're mistaken.
This isn't a question of one person
deciding, one deciding vote.
This is like any other company.
We have directors and very old rules.
The Pope himself
would have to approve you.
We've sold the casinos.
All businesses having to do
with gambling.
We have no interests or investments
in anything illegitimate.
The Corleones are prepared to deposit
500 million dollars in the Vatican Bank
when Mr Corleone receives
majority control of lmmobiliare.
lmmobiliare could be something new.
A European conglomerate.
Few families have control
of such a company.
lt seems that, in today's world,
the power to absolve debt is greater
than the power of forgiveness.
600 million dollars.
Don't overestimate
the power of forgiveness.
Don Corleone,
this deal with lmmobiliare can make you
one of the richest men in the world.
Your whole past history, and the history
of your family, would be washed away.
600 million.
The motion under discussion
relates to Corleone Group's proposal
to acquire 1 00,000,000 newly-issued
Class A voting shares.
... Corleone capital invested directly
into lnternational lmmobiliare,
an old and respected
European company.
Mr Corleone has an ambitious programme
to expand this real estate company
into an international conglomerate...
...by Eastern techniques of efficiency
and focus and unlimited...
Mr Corleone, excuse me.
Didn't you recently deposit 200 million
in the Vatican Bank,
which is affiliated with lmmobiliare?
True. Why not?
Wasn't there any questioning about
the timing on this particular deposit?
Mr Chairman, if l may?
The Vito Andolini Corleone Foundation,
of which Mary Corleone is chairman,
has made an endowment
of 1 00 million dollars.
The money comes from his own family
and will be administered by the Vatican.
Does that answer your question?
l have always believed that helping your
fellow man is profitable in every sense,
personally and bottom line.
My fellow shareholders, if Europe
and America can learn to co-operate,
if we can learn to pool our wealth,
share our markets,
we can defeat any competition
anywhere in the world.
Thank you for your time.
l hope that you will look favourably
on my proposal. Thank you.
Let me have this microphone here.
Will we let a criminal run our company?
He's got the map of Sicily on his face!
Order!
He's either a Catholic or a mafioso...
The Hamilton lnvestors Group
cannot support this proposal.
Your Excellency...
Mr Chairman...
...the Vatican Bank feels
that lnternational lmmobiliare...
...will be safe in Mr Corleone's hands.
...subject to audit and final ratification,
which must take place in Rome.
Please join me in welcoming
Mr Michael Corleone.
Dad?
Tony says that l'm a front
for the foundation.
That you're using me to pull the strings.
- To get the money where you want it.
- Please!
- To shine up your public image.
- Mary!
Mary, this is real.
This foundation is real.
l wanted Anthony to be part of it.
l thought you would be together on this.
l won't interfere.
l'll help, but only if you ask.
What is this really for?
Why are you doing this?
Why am l doing this?
l'm doing this for my children.
You're doing it for your children too.
This foundation is supposed to
help all people?
That's the purpose.
This is legitimate.
Mary, l swear, this is legitimate.
Dad, l want this to bring me
closer to you.
l would burn in Hell to keep you safe.
Go in the other car. l'll ride with Michael.
Go, go, go.
As your family's oldest friend, l'm
always chosen to bring you messages.
Tell me, Don Altobello.
Your old partners are grateful for
the money you made them.
They worship you...
...but their hearts are broken, because
they think you abandoned them.
They want to share your deal
on lmmobiliare, to be a family again.
lt can purify their money.
This l cannot do.
lmmobiliare must be legitimate.
l know.
But they're unhappy.
And you?
l ask nothing for myself,
only peace in my old age.
But l must please the world around me.
Michael, your father was a
reasonable man. Learn from him.
l learned many things from my father.
Call a meeting, my friend,
so there are no debts or grudges.
We will make the peace, you and l.
The Vatican announced today...
that Pope Paul Vl has canceled
his Sunday blessing...
due to ill health.
His physician has ordered
total bedrest...
and cessation of all activities.
They've had a press conference. The
Pope's condition is grave. ''Gravissimo. ''
The purpose of this meeting
is to ratify...
the motion passed by our
shareholders in New York.
Please...
Our group represents a consortium
of Catholic businessmen
against the Corleone control.
The Vatican has cast its vote. Corleone
Group already controls the Board.
According to the Lateran Treaty,
the Vatican vote must be ratified here.
Here in Rome, by the Pope.
The Pope is gravely ill.
Until he recovers, l am powerless.
- What if he dies?
- Then...
...as you Americans say,
all bets are off.
Gentlemen, please.
This is a brief delay. Nothing more.
Your Excellency, gentlemen...
l advise you to join us in our prayers
for the Holy Father's recovery.
We had an agreement!
This meeting was to be
merely a formality.
- Please sit down.
- l'd rather stand. Give me an answer.
The lmmobiliare has its roots in the
European tradition. Please understand.
l understand.
Your tactics are despicable.
That's quite an indictment,
coming from a Corleone.
- Gentlemen, gentlemen!
- Remember you are in the Vatican.
- What is it that you want?
- Yes, you will take control.
We'll gladly put you at the helm
of our little fleet,
but our ships must all sail
in the same direction.
Otherwise, who can say how long
your stay with us will last?
lt's not personal. lt's only business.
You should know, Godfather.
Very well.
You want to do business with me?
l will do business with you.
Vipers, all of them.
- We're back with the Borgias!
- Uncle Michael...
- Andrew!
- l heard you were here.
lt's so nice to see you.
Vincent, it's so nice.
What is this about the Borgias?
Those days are over.
- Recognise it?
- Yeah.
Genco Olive Oil. That's where our
grandfather started as a delivery boy.
Three years later he owned it.
- Only in America.
- That's it.
Vincenzo, where have you been hiding?
We need your help so badly.
- What can l do for you?
- Get rid of Joe Zasa. He sells drugs...
Now that l'm an older woman,
l'm afraid to go out at night.
Where should they be now?
- Lou, what's going on?
- We're late.
- Have l ever let you down?
- l trust you.
- Don't worry.
- Thank you.
Enjoy yourselves.
- What was that?
- The neighbourhood's in trouble.
- Do you keep an eye out for them?
- Yes.
- And for me?
- From now on.
- l've missed you all this time.
- l missed you too, cousin.
l missed growing up with my cousins.
l didn't even know you, but missed you.
Do you remember stories
about our fathers? The old days?
Yeah, what do you want to know?
- What was Sonny like?
- Well, he was the Prince of the City.
He died before l was born,
but l've heard a lot about him.
- What about my father?
- He's a great man.
He's a hero. He saved the family.
- Vincent?
- What?
Did he kill his own brother?
No.
So, it's all lies?
Just stories, sweetheart. Okay?
Okay.
l believe you.
- l'm glad you're around.
- l'm glad you're here too.
Cugina...
Cous...
l'd like to take Joey Zasa for a ride
in this and drop him.
Joey Zasa is nothing.
He's a small-time enforcer.
He bluffs and threatens.
He's nothing. You can see him coming
a mile away.
- We should kill him before he...
- No!
Never hate your enemies.
lt affects your judgement.
Nice to see you again, Mr Corleone.
Hey, girls. Let's go.
We trusted you to manage
our money in the casinos.
lt's not even 20 years. You've sold the
casinos and made fortunes for all of us.
Bravo, Don Corleone!
Thank you.
Friends, l have come here
because our business together is done.
We have prospered,
and now it is time for us to dissolve
the business relationship between us.
That's it.